Finding Aid for League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights records, 1953-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights records
1953-1978
League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights.
85272 Bm 2
Records of Dearborn and Dearborn Heights chapters of the League of Women Voters and (after April 1972) of the combined chapter; include minutes, newsletters, issue files, correspondence, files of study committees, and voter guides and other voter information.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the League (donor no. 6889 ) on January 20, 1983.
The record group is open to research.
The League of Women Voters is a nonpartisan, volunteer organization whose purpose is to promote political responsibility through the informed and active participation of citizens in government. Its major concern is voter education, and before most elections, it publishes a voters guide with information about the candidates and the various ballot proposals. The League also sponsors public forums, interviews candidates, and otherwise works to get out the vote. As a nonpartisan group, the League does not take a position on political parties or candidates, only on issues, and only after it has made a thorough study of the subject and its membership has reached a consensus.
The development of the Dearborn-Dearborn Heights League of Women is somewhat more complicated than other local leagues. It began first as a unit discussion group of the Detroit LWV. Here the group studied a wide range of Detroit, state, and national issues, but very little about local Dearborn affairs. As a result, the leadership of this group began working to have their own league chapter. In March 1951, a provisional league was formed; in December 1951, that provisional league was formally recognized as the League of Women Voters of Dearborn.
With the growth and development of this area of the state in the 1950's and 1960's, some felt there might be a need for a separate league for Dearborn Heights. A provisional league was recognized in 1967, but after five years, its members voted to disband. At the same time as that dissolution, April 20, 1972, the members of the Dearborn LWV voted to reorganize, enlarging the basis of their organization, and changing its name to the League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights.
The records of the League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights have been arranged into four series: Dearborn league files, Dearborn Heights league files, State Programs, National Programs, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Dearborn (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Dearborn Heights (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Elections--Michigan--Dearborn Heights.; Elections--Michigan--Dearborn.; League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights.; Women--Michigan--Dearborn Heights--Societies and clubs.; Women--Michigan--Dearborn--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dearborn (Mich.); Dearborn Heights (Mich.); Hubbard, Orville Liscum, 1903-1982.; League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights.; Political organizations.; Women--Political life.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Dearborn LWV Files, 1953-1978
  The Dearborn league files covers the years 1953 to 1978, with most of the papers falling in the period of 1961-1975. Included are minutes of annual meetings and board meetings, correspondence, newsletters, local program files, study committee files, and Voter Service guides and working files. Studies undertaken by the league ranged over a number of topics, including the Dearborn school system, environmental quality, the welfare system, and the relationship between the Michigan courts and the juveniles and children brought before them. The records created after April 20, 1972 are of the merged League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights.
  - Annual Meetings
    - 1961-1974, 11 folders (Box 1)
      (lacking 1974)
  - Board Meetings
    - 1961-March 1974, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Board Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws, 1960-1971 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1965-1975, 1978; 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Beebe, Senator Lorraine, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Craig, Senator Roger, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Dingell, Representative John D., 1967-1971; 1973 (Box 1)
    - Griffin, Senator Robert P., 1967; 1969-1971; 1973 (Box 1)
    - Hart, Senator Philip A., 1967; 1969; 1971; 1973 (Box 1)
    - McCollough, Representative Lucille H., 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Pilch, Representative Alex, 1967-1968; 1972 (Box 1)
  - Council on Human Relations, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Crisis in Education-Public Forum, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Dearborn Advisory Committee on Busing and Property Tax, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Dearborn and Its Government, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Dearborn Voter (Newsletter)
    (name changes to The Voter with September 1973 issue)
    - 1952-1969, 9 folders (Box 1)
      (lacking 1964)
    - 1970-1975, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary of the League of Women Voters, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Financial Records
    - Auditor's Reports, 1966-1972 (Box 2)
    - Budgets, 1961-1962; 1966-1972 (Box 2)
    - Finance Advisors
      - 1962, 1964-1968; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Finance Drive, 1967-1968; 1971 (Box 2)
    - Metropolitan Finance Committee, 1963-1968 (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1960-1961; 1966-1974 (Box 2)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1965-1974 (Box 2)
  - Human Resources, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Job Corps, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Job Descriptions of League Officers, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
  - Know Your Wayne County Government (Box 2)
  - Lake Erie Basin Committee, 1966-1969; 1971 (Box 2)
  - Local Program
    - City Charter, 1967-1968; 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - City Planning
      - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Clippings relating to local programs (Box 2)
    - Dearborn schools, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Dearborn School Millage, 1966; 1969 (Box 2)
    - Juvenile Services, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Metropolitan Regional Planning, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Program Planning, 1966; 1968-1972 (Box 2)
    - Wayne County Home Rule, 1966-1974 (Box 2)
  - Mayor's Breakfast
    - 1967 (Box 2)
      (Northwestern Wayne County Child Guidance Clinic)
    - 1968 (Box 2)
      (Let's Get the Courts out of Politics)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
      (Detroit Regional Transportation and Land Use Study)
  - Meet the League, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Fund, Inc. (Southeast Michigan Regionalism), 1972 (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Integration Study Committee (School Desegregation), 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1977 (Box 2)
  - A Morning with Your State Legislators
    - 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1972 (Box 2)
  - Non-Partisan Policy, 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Outdoor Sanctuary in Dearborn, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Overseas Education Fund (Visit of Multinational Seminar to Detroit), 1973 (Box 2)
  - Policies and Procedures, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
  - Public Relations
    - 1953-1954, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Report to the Community, 1965-1972 (Box 2)
  - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments, 1967-1972 (Box 2)
  - Speakers Bureau, 1964-1965; 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Study Committees
    - Dearborn Schools
      - Accreditation, 1962-1965 (Box 2)
      - Administrative Organization, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - Citizens' Educational Advisory Committee, 1964 (Box 2)
      - Clippings Committee Minutes, 1963 (Box 2)
      - Committee Reports to LWV Board, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence
        - 1958, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
        - 1965, 1969 (Box 2)
      - Curriculum, 1963-1968 (Box 2)
      - Dropout Study Educating Today's Child for Tomorrow's World-Skit (Box 2)
      - Henry Ford Community College
        - Development Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
        - Informational Material (Box 3)
        - Millage, 1958 (Box 3)
      - Interviews, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      - Material for Publication, Dearborn Schools (Box 3)
      - Program Material, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
      - Publications of Dearborn Schools
        - Department of Pupil Personnel-Bulletins, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous Publications, 1961-1967 (Box 3)
        - Report Card to the Community, 1954; 1959-1960 (Box 3)
        - Superintendent's Report, 1953; 1961-1964 (Box 3)
      - Questionnaires, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      - Reports
        - Dearborn Civic Committee on School Needs, 1960 (Box 3)
        - The League Looks at Schools, 1956 (Box 3)
        - School Study Committee Reports, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
        - Superior Achiever's Project, 1962-1965 (Box 3)
      - School Finance, 1956; 1958; 1964; 1967 (Box 3)
      - Wayne County Community College, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Environmental Quality
      - Agriculture, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Committee Reports to LWV Board, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
      - Consensus Meeting Reports, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Housing, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous papers relating to land use (Box 3)
      - Property Tax (Box 3)
      - Recreation-Clippings (Box 3)
      - Soil Erosion and Sedimentation, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
      - Urban Problems, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - Examining the Presidency, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Grass Roots, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Courts-Juveniles and Children
      - Clippings, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
      - Consensus Report, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
      - Papers relating to Judicial System (Box 3)
    - River Rouge Basin, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    - Welfare
      - Committee Reports to LWV Board, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Consensus Reports
        - 1964-1965 (Box 3)
        - 1966-1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence
        - 1963-1964 (Box 3)
        - 1965-1968 (Box 3)
      - Interviews
        - 1964 (Box 3)
        - 1966 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous papers relating to welfare (Box 3)
      - Poverty Implications: Migrant Workers and Indiana, 1964 (Box 3)
      - Program Material
        - 1963-1964 (Box 3)
        - 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Surveys of Agencies and Unmet Needs, 1966 (Box 3)
  - UM-Dearborn Early Learning and Child Development Center, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Urban Renewal-Southeast Dearborn, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Voters Service
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1959; 1961; 1963; 1965-1968 (Box 3)
    - Guides and other materials relating to elections, 1953; 1957; 1960-1973; 15 folders (Box 4)
    - Interviews
      - 1952, 1959; 1961; 1963; 1967-1969 (Box 4)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - Dingell, Representative John D., 1966-1972; 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Let's All Vote, 1962-1965; 1967-1969; 1971 (Box 4)
    - Television Forum-Your State Senate: The Candidates, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Voter Education-Lecture-Discussion Series, You and Your Government, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Voter Registration, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Voters Service Reports to LWV Board, 1959-1966; 1970; 1972 (Box 4)
    - Wayne County Intermediate School District Reorganization, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Wayne County Voters Service Committee, 1960; 1966; 1968 (Box 4)
  - Washington, D. C. Petition Drive, 1970 (Box 4)
- Dearborn Heights LVW Files, 1965-1972
  The Dearborn Heights files covers the years 1965 to 1972, the period before the reorganization of the Dearborn LWV into the LWV of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights. Material about Dearborn Heights after 1972 will be found in the Dearborn series. The Dearborn Heights files also includes minutes of board meetings, newsletters, and Voter Service material. Some of the subject files in this series concerned the Crestwood School Board recall and a study of police-community relations.
  - Board Meetings
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968 (Box 4)
    - 1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1965-1970 (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Crestwood School Board Recall Election, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Dearborn Heights, City With a Future, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Local Study-Police and the Community (Box 4)
  - Newsletter (Bulletin and Dearborn Heights Voter)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Voters Service
    - Correspondence, 1967-1971; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Guides, 1966-1967; 1969; 1971 (Box 4)
- State Programs, 1964-1973
  Of special interest in the State Programs series is the Call to Action. Once the League has taken a position on a bill before the state legislature, and that bill is at a "critical point" in the legislature process, the League will issue a Call to Action asking the local leagues and other interested parties to make known to the appropriate legislators the League's position. This step is taken only with bills considered "vital" by the League.
  - Call to Action
    - 1965, 1967-1968; 1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Emergency Housing Proposal, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Programs
    - Pesticides, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Proposal C (Re Aid to Non-Public Schools), 1970 (Box 4)
    - Recommendations for State Program, 1964-1967 (Box 4)
    - Taxation and Education, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - State Convention in Dearborn, May 1965 1964-1966 (Box 4)
- National Programs, 1965-1973
  The National Programs series includes several files relating to the League's position on national issues. There is also a folder of Time for Action which is similar to the Call for Action on the state level, except that the issues are national in scope.
  - Air Pollution Control, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
  - Electoral College, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Policy (UN and Foreign Aid), 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Home Rule for Washington, DC, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Human Resources (Welfare), 1967-1970 (Box 4)
  - Water Resources, 1965-1968 (Box 4)
  - Time for Action, 1965-1969 (Box 4)
- Photographs
  - Photos of proclamation ceremonies with Mayor Orville Hubbard participating